<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Peder M. Isager</title>
    <link>https://pedermisager.org/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Peder M. Isager</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://pedermisager.org/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Netlify</title>
      <link>https://pedermisager.org/collection/day02/01-netlify/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pedermisager.org/collection/day02/01-netlify/</guid>
      <description>So far, we&amp;rsquo;ve been leveraging GitHub Pages for publishing. This works great, but for blogdown we&amp;rsquo;ll start using Netlify. Let&amp;rsquo;s start RIGHT NOW with a site we&amp;rsquo;ve already built and published.
Pre-requisites Pick either your postcards site, or your distill site from day 01. Refresh your memory- which repository was it again?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A GitHub profile</title>
      <link>https://pedermisager.org/collection/day01/01-github/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pedermisager.org/collection/day01/01-github/</guid>
      <description>Profile https://docs.github.com/en/github/setting-up-and-managing-your-github-profile/personalizing-your-profile
Pin projects to profile https://docs.github.com/en/github/setting-up-and-managing-your-github-profile/pinning-items-to-your-profile
Profile README This is new! Let&amp;rsquo;s do it:
https://docs.github.com/en/github/setting-up-and-managing-your-github-profile/managing-your-profile-readme</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Prework</title>
      <link>https://pedermisager.org/collection/prework/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pedermisager.org/collection/prework/</guid>
      <description>Welcome to the Introducing Yourself Online workshop! We look forward to meeting you. Before attending the workshop, please complete the following prework.
Set up RStudio Cloud Sign up for a free RStudio Cloud account at https://rstudio.cloud/ before the workshop. I recommend logging in with an existing Google or GitHub account, if you have one (rather than creating a new account with another password you have to remember). I want you to be able to work from your own laptop in this workshop, but Cloud is an important back-up plan should you run into troubles.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A postcard</title>
      <link>https://pedermisager.org/collection/day01/02-postcards/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pedermisager.org/collection/day01/02-postcards/</guid>
      <description>Pre-requisites First, make sure you have the latest version of the postcards package installed from CRAN:
install.packages(&amp;#34;postcards&amp;#34;) Restart your R session. If you use RStudio, use the menu item Session &amp;gt; Restart R or the associated keyboard shortcut:
Ctrl + Shift + F10 (Windows and Linux) or Command + Shift + F10 (Mac OS). packageVersion(&amp;#34;postcards&amp;#34;) [1] ‘0.2.0’ Create GitHub repo Online.
Clone GitHub repo usethis::create_from_github(&amp;#34;https://github.com/apreshill/global-postcard.git&amp;#34;) ✨ Commit &amp;amp; Push! ✨</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using blogdown</title>
      <link>https://pedermisager.org/collection/day02/02-blogdown/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pedermisager.org/collection/day02/02-blogdown/</guid>
      <description>Pre-requisites First, make sure you have the latest version of the blogdown package installed from CRAN:
install.packages(&amp;#34;blogdoown&amp;#34;) Restart your R session. If you use RStudio, use the menu item Session &amp;gt; Restart R or the associated keyboard shortcut:
Ctrl + Shift + F10 (Windows and Linux) or Command + Shift + F10 (Mac OS). packageVersion(&amp;#34;blogdown&amp;#34;) [1] ‘1.0’ Create GitHub repo Online.
Clone GitHub repo usethis::create_from_github(&amp;#34;https://github.com/apreshill/global-blogdown.git&amp;#34;) ✨ Commit &amp;amp; Push! ✨</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A distill site</title>
      <link>https://pedermisager.org/collection/day01/03-distill/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pedermisager.org/collection/day01/03-distill/</guid>
      <description>Pre-requisites First, make sure you have the latest version of the distill package installed from CRAN:
install.packages(&amp;quot;distill&amp;quot;) Restart your R session. If you use RStudio, use the menu item Session &amp;gt; Restart R or the associated keyboard shortcut:
Ctrl + Shift + F10 (Windows and Linux) or Command + Shift + F10 (Mac OS). &amp;lt;!-- --&amp;gt; packageVersion(&amp;quot;distill&amp;quot;) [1] ‘1.2’ Create GitHub repo Online.
Clone GitHub repo usethis::create_from_github(&amp;quot;https://github.com/apreshill/global-distill.git&amp;quot;) ✨ Commit &amp;amp; Push!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Warm woolen mittens</title>
      <link>https://pedermisager.org/collection/day02/03-blogdown/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pedermisager.org/collection/day02/03-blogdown/</guid>
      <description> Hi, I&#39;m the here-bot cat! Use me to find your way in your website.
Here I am: content/collection\day02\03-blogdown\index.md To remove me, delete this line inside that file: {{&amp;lt; here &amp;gt;}}
My content section is: collection My layout is: single-series part 2! does this work? now for some very cool things more get ready! </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Which variables to control for, and why</title>
      <link>https://pedermisager.org/blog/why-experiments-are-considered-gold-standard-for-answering-causal-questions/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pedermisager.org/blog/why-experiments-are-considered-gold-standard-for-answering-causal-questions/</guid>
      <description>In this post, we will use a practical example to explore the power of statistical control, explaining why adjusting for the right variables clarifies relationships and why adjusting for the wrong ones can introduce new, serious biases.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why experiments are considered gold standard for answering causal questions</title>
      <link>https://pedermisager.org/blog/why-experiments-are-considered-gold-standard-for-answering-causal-questions/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pedermisager.org/blog/why-experiments-are-considered-gold-standard-for-answering-causal-questions/</guid>
      <description>In this blog post, I will briefly explain why experimental designs are considered so valuable by scientists and why we often insist that randomized experiments are necessary for answering causal questions. I will use a practical example to illustrate this point. If you&amp;rsquo;re new to the concept of causal inference, it may be helpful to read my earlier blog posts on &lt;em&gt;correlation vs. causation&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;eight basic rules for causal inference.&lt;/em&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Eight basic rules for causal inference</title>
      <link>https://pedermisager.org/blog/eight_basic_rules_for_causal_inference/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pedermisager.org/blog/eight_basic_rules_for_causal_inference/</guid>
      <description>In this blog post I will describe eight basic rules that govern the relationship between causal mechanisms in the real world and associations/correlations we can observe in data. To make each rule as easy as possible to understand, I will describe each rule both in words and in causal graph and logic terms, and I will offer some very simple simulation R code for each rule to demonstrate how it works in practice.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Four one-sided test of significance (FOST). Dear reader, does this make sense?</title>
      <link>https://pedermisager.org/blog/four-one-sided-test/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pedermisager.org/blog/four-one-sided-test/</guid>
      <description>In this blog post I propose a four one-sided test of significance (FOST) that can be used to test whether an effect is smaller than OR larger than OR equivalent to the smallest effect size of interest. I lay out the general setup and interpretation of FOST, and ask readers to help me evaluate its validity.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why does correlation not equal causation?</title>
      <link>https://pedermisager.org/blog/why_does_correlation_not_equal_causation/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pedermisager.org/blog/why_does_correlation_not_equal_causation/</guid>
      <description>In this blog post I will explain why it makes sense to think about causal explanations when we see correlation, why correlation does not always imply causation, and which alternative causal models to consider when you are trying to figure out why two variables in your data are correlated. The blog post is intended as a non-technical introduction. I use only words and pictures to explain all concepts and logic, and I use a hypothetical example from health psychology to illustrate. The post should be relevant to anyone who is interested in using data to understand causal mechanisms.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What is Worth Replicating? - SIPS 2020 Unconference session</title>
      <link>https://pedermisager.org/blog/what-is-worth-replicating/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pedermisager.org/blog/what-is-worth-replicating/</guid>
      <description>Given that most research is original and we have limited resources available for replication, we need guidelines for study selection in replication research. But what makes a study worth replicating? In our unconference session at SIPS this year, we had the pleasure of discussing this problem with fifty-some enthusiastic scholars. Here is a quick summary of what they taught us.
First off, we went into this session with our own prior beliefs about what makes a study worth replicating.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Choosing what to replicate - Efficient study selection in the modern age.</title>
      <link>https://pedermisager.org/talk/2020_riots_choosing_what_to_replicate/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pedermisager.org/talk/2020_riots_choosing_what_to_replicate/</guid>
      <description> </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fifty ways to leave your model</title>
      <link>https://pedermisager.org/blog/fifty-ways-to-leave-your-model/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pedermisager.org/blog/fifty-ways-to-leave-your-model/</guid>
      <description>A method for calculating the number of alternative causal models, given a number of variables/nodes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Meta-research at the Psychological Science Accelerator</title>
      <link>https://pedermisager.org/blog/meta-research-at-the-psa/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pedermisager.org/blog/meta-research-at-the-psa/</guid>
      <description>Summary of unconference session at Tilburg Meta-research day 2019.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mixed model equivalence test using R and PANGEA</title>
      <link>https://pedermisager.org/blog/mixed_model_equivalence/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pedermisager.org/blog/mixed_model_equivalence/</guid>
      <description>How to calculate an equivalence test, and power for an equivalence test, for a fixed effect in a mixed effects model using R and PANGEA.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Proposing a theory committee at the Psychological Science Accelerator</title>
      <link>https://pedermisager.org/blog/psa-theory-committee/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pedermisager.org/blog/psa-theory-committee/</guid>
      <description>(written in collaboration with Nicholas A. Coles)
The Psychological Science Accelerator (PSA) is a global network of psychological laboratories that organizes large-scale empirical research projects. The organization aims “to accelerate the accumulation of reliable and generalizable evidence in psychological science” (Moshontz et al. 2018). To succeed in this mission, the PSA has created several committees that work together to address important challenges in producing high quality research, such as having access to an inferentially meaningful sample size, reducing the reliance on WEIRD participants, and improving the methodological quality of designs and analyses.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tachyons for Style</title>
      <link>https://pedermisager.org/project/giraffes/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pedermisager.org/project/giraffes/</guid>
      <description>Tachyons is a design system that allows you to design gorgeous interfaces in the browser with little effort. Because Speed Building this static site generator theme was the first time I used an Atomic (or Functional) CSS system like Tachyons. It&amp;rsquo;s a design system that provides very small (which means fast) CSS modules that you can use in your HTML. So, rather than writing every line of CSS, you apply the style you need as you write your HTML with easy to understand shorthand class names.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Palmer Penguins</title>
      <link>https://pedermisager.org/project/penguins/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pedermisager.org/project/penguins/</guid>
      <description>“Grid is the very first CSS module created specifically to solve the layout problems we&amp;rsquo;ve all been hacking our way around for as long as we&amp;rsquo;ve been making websites.” — Chris House, A Complete Guide to CSS Grid Layout 1
Since I began building websites in Y2K, I&amp;rsquo;ve lost count how many times the phrase &amp;ldquo;&amp;hellip;there&amp;rsquo;s got to be a better way to do this&amp;rdquo; has passed my lips. Most times, while fighting with floats and widths of content and sidebars or just basically trying to get something beside something else without using a stupid TABLE.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bakeoff</title>
      <link>https://pedermisager.org/project/bakeoff/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pedermisager.org/project/bakeoff/</guid>
      <description>Formspree makes it easy to receive submissions from HTML forms on your static website. Functional Form This theme has a form-to-email feature built in, thanks to the simple Formspree integration. All you need to activate the form is a valid recipient email address saved in the front matter of the form (/content/forms/contact.md). Of course, the example shown below (your@email.here) must not be used. Please use your actual email address.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quantifying the corroboration of a finding</title>
      <link>https://pedermisager.org/blog/quantifying-the-corroboration-of-a-finding/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pedermisager.org/blog/quantifying-the-corroboration-of-a-finding/</guid>
      <description>A summary of the pros and cons of multiple candidate statistics.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Contact</title>
      <link>https://pedermisager.org/contact/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Feb 2019 13:38:41 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pedermisager.org/contact/</guid>
      <description>** Contact page don&amp;rsquo;t contain a body, just the front matter above. See form.html in the layouts folder.
Formspree requires a (free) account and new form to be set up. The link is made on the final published url in the field: Restrict to Domain. It is possible to register up to 2 emails free and you can select which one you want the forms to go to within Formspree in the Settings tab.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Typography Styles &amp; Element Examples</title>
      <link>https://pedermisager.org/elements/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Feb 2019 12:27:33 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pedermisager.org/elements/</guid>
      <description>Font Sizes A A A A A A A A 6rem
(96px) 5rem
(80px) 3rem
(48px) 2.25rem
(36px) 1.5rem
(24px) 1.25rem
(20px) 1rem
(16px) .875rem
(14px) Type Samples Head&amp;shy;line Sub&amp;shy;head&amp;shy;line Level 1 Heading One page to rule them all...well, not really. This page displays sample typography and page elements to illustrate their style. Things like headings and paragraphs showing the beautiful type scale, form elements, tabular data, and image layouts just to name a few.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to share your data online with OSF</title>
      <link>https://pedermisager.org/blog/how-to-share-your-data-with-osf/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pedermisager.org/blog/how-to-share-your-data-with-osf/</guid>
      <description>The Open Science movement is here to stay. However, incorporating open practices like data sharing into your work flow can seem like a challenging task. If you have never made data available online before, the process can feel a bit daunting. Where should I put the data? What should I put up? What do I need to consider before I do it? In this post I will take you through a practical example of how to share data using the Open Science Frameword (OSF) platform.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ganging Up on Psychological Science</title>
      <link>https://pedermisager.org/blog/ganging-up-on-psych-science/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pedermisager.org/blog/ganging-up-on-psych-science/</guid>
      <description>Sometimes, the costs of doing good science outgrow the resources available to the individual scientist. Large scale collaboration projects are quickly becoming our best tool for dealing with this problem in psychology.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What to Replicate?</title>
      <link>https://pedermisager.org/blog/what-to-replicate/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pedermisager.org/blog/what-to-replicate/</guid>
      <description>Justifications of study choice from 85 replication studies.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Contributors</title>
      <link>https://pedermisager.org/contributors/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pedermisager.org/contributors/</guid>
      <description>Thank you to all the folks who have contributed both technical and creative skills to this project:
Desirée De Leon 🦒 (designed 5 of the custom color themes, made illustrations for the workshop, and provided general aesthetic feedback along the way)
Garrick Aden-Buie 🧙‍♀️ (debugged headroom.js and lent his panelset.js code to the theme)
Allison Horst 🐕 (awesome illustrations of campfires, seedlings, and evergreens, as well as my R Markdown hedgehog mascot 🦔)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Curriculum Vitae</title>
      <link>https://pedermisager.org/files/cv/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pedermisager.org/files/cv/</guid>
      <description>Lovisenberggata 13email: peder.isager@oslonh.no0456 Oslotwitter: @peder_isagerNorwayphone: 0047 976 51 974Education2017-2022Doctor’s degree; Eindhoven University of Technology
Specializations: Research methods, statistics, replication.
Thesis title: Deciding what to replicate.
Thesis link: https://pure.tue.nl/ws/portalfiles/portal/200554284/20220524_Isager_hf.pdf.
Supervisors: Daniël Lakens, Anna van ’t Veer, Chris Snijders.
2015-2017Master’s degree, Cognitive Neuroscience; University of Oslo
Specializations: Psychopharmacology, fMRI.
Thesis title: \(\mu\)-Opioid Modulation of Reported Wanting of Palatable Food Images.
Thesis link: https://doi.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>License</title>
      <link>https://pedermisager.org/license/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pedermisager.org/license/</guid>
      <description>My blog posts are released under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
